Guide to the William Wordsworth collection, 1656-1987
Wordsworth, William collection, 1656-1987
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William Wordsworth collection, 1656-1987 (bulk 1798-1850)
4621
William Wordsworth, 1770-1850.
35.8 linear ft.
Letters, manuscripts, broadsides, pictures, documents, and objects.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Items relating to Wordsworth and his family. Includes first drafts of poems written by Wordsworth. Also included are manuscripts by Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Sara Hutchinson, Dorothy Wordsworth, Mary Wordsworth, Thomas De Quincey, Robert Southey, Lord Byron, and John Keats.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
English poet, one of the founders of the Romantic movement in English literature.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters, manuscripts, broadsides, pictures, documents, and objects by, to, belonging to, or about Wordsworth and his family. Includes first drafts of poems Wordsworth later published in Yarrow Revisited (1835); 51 of the sonnets published in Ecclesiastical Sketches, in an early fair copy before final revision for publication; manuscripts of 10 additional sonnets sent to Wordsworth's first American editor, Prof. Henry Reed; and a transcript made before publication of the poem "Composed Upon an Evening of Extraordinary Splendour and Beauty." Also included are manuscripts by Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Sara Hutchinson, Dorothy Wordsworth, Mary Wordsworth, Thomas De Quincey, Robert Southey, Lord Byron, and John Keats. Byron manuscript is a draft of an unfinished short story; Keats manuscript is a fragment of his poem "Isabella." Coleridge manuscripts include a first version of "Dejection: An Ode," a draft of a variant of "The Eolian Harp," and other poems; fragments of essays; and notes on Schiller's plays The Piccolomini and The Death of Wallenstein.
Correspondence includes letters between the Wordsworth family and Henry Reed; letters from the Wordsworths to George Huntly Gordon, former secretary to Sir Walter Scott; correspondence with fellow writers such as Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Robert Southey, and Thomas De Quincey; and extensive correspondence among members of the Hutchinson, Monkhouse, and Wordsworth families. Also included are a few letters each from Thomas Carlyle, Walter Savage Landor, Percy Bysshe Shelley, and Thomas Babington Macaulay. In addition, there are letters concerning the building of the Wordsworth Collection, from Cynthia Morgan St. John and Lane Cooper. Other correspondents include Elizabeth Smith Aders, John T. Barker, James Dykes Campbell, Catherine Clarkson, Derwent Coleridge, Sara Coleridge, Joseph Cottle, William Rowan Hamilton, John Louis Haney, Benjamin Robert Haydon, Herbert Hill, Hannah Hoare, Leonard Huxley, William Jackson, William Angus Knight, Charles Lamb, Charles and Sophia Lloyd, Thomas Manning, Basil Montagu, Edward Moxon, Winthrop Mackworth Praed, Edward Quillinan, Henry Crabb Robinson, Thomas Noon Talfourd, Jonathan Walton, John Wilson.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850.; Aders, Elizabeth Smith.; Barker, John T.; Byron, George Gordon Byron, 1788-1824.; Campbell, James Dykes, 1838-1895.; Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881.; Clarkson, Catherine.; Coleridge, Derwent, 1800-1883.; Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834.; Coleridge, Sara Coleridge, 1802-1852.; Cottle, Joseph, 1770-1853.; De Quincey, Thomas, 1785-1859.; Gordon, George Huntly, 1798-1868.; Hamilton, William Rowan, 1805-1865.; Haney, John Louis, 1877-1960.; Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1786-1846.; Hill, Herbert, 1810-1892.; Hoare, Hannah.; Hutchinson family.; Hutchinson, Elizabeth, 1820-1905.; Hutchinson, Joanna, 1780-1843.; Hutchinson, John, 1768-1833.; Hutchinson, Mary Monkhouse, 1787-1858.; Hutchinson, Sara, 1775-1835.; Hutchinson, Thomas, 1773-1849.; Huxley, Leonard, 1860-1933.; Jackson, William.; Keats, John, 1795-1821.; Knight, William Angus, 1836-1916.; Lamb, Charles, 1775-1834.; Landor, Walter Savage, 1775-1864.; Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839.; Lloyd, Sophia Pemberton, d. 1839.; Macaulay, Thomas Babington Macaulay, 1800-1859.; Manning, Thomas, 1772-1840.; Monkhouse family.; Monkhouse, George, 1756-1802.; Monkhouse, John, 1782-1866.; Monkhouse, Thomas, 1783-1825.; Montagu, Basil, 1770-1851.; Moxon, Edward, 1801-1858.; Praed, Winthrop Mackworth, 1802-1839.; Quillinan, Edward, 1791-1851.; Reed, Henry, 1808-1854.; Robinson, Henry Crabb, 1775-1867.; Shelley, Percy Bysshe, 1792-1822.; Southey, Robert, 1774-1843.; Talfourd, Thomas Noon, 1795-1854.; Walton, Jonathan, 1774-1846.; Wilson, John, 1785-1854.; Wordsworth family.; Wordsworth, Charles, 1806-1892.; Wordsworth, Christopher, 1774-1846.; Wordsworth, Christopher, 1807-1885.; Wordsworth, Dora, 1804-1847.; Wordsworth, Dorothy, 1771-1855.; Wordsworth, Gordon Graham, 1860-1935.; Wordsworth, John, 1805-1840.; Wordsworth, Mary, 1770-1859.; Wordsworth, Susanna Frere.; Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850.; Wordsworth, William, 1810-1883.
Subjects:
English literature--19th century.; Romanticism--England.; Domestic relations--England.; Women authors--England.; Authors, English.
Places:
England--Intellectual life--19th century.; England--Description and travel.
Form and Genre Terms:
Portraits.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
The container list below currently includes only the bound manuscript items in the collection.
Dove Cottage manuscripts are reproductions of the originals.
RELATED MATERIALS
Large collection of books by and about Wordsworth is also held in the repository, including all editions of his published works, books from his personal library, and works on the Lake District.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Organized into the following series: Bound manuscripts; documents; reviews, pamphlets, etc.; letters by Wordsworth; letters to Wordsworth, together with manuscripts by other writers; objects; broadsides; portraits and other pictures.
Bound manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title keyword; letters by Wordsworth, in chronological order; and letters to Wordsworth, alphabetically by correspondent.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Loose Manuscripts
Correspondence and Manuscripts By and To Others
Series II. Bound Manuscripts
Series III. Wordsworthiana and Other Material
Series IV. Dove Cottage manuscripts, photocopies
CONTAINER LIST
- Loose Manuscripts
  - Manuscripts and Documents (Box 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1796-1829 (Box 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1830-1836 (Box 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1837-1843 (Box 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1844-1850, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and Manuscripts By and To Others
    - A-B (Box 7)
    - C-Col (Box 8)
    - Coleridge, Samuel Taylor manuscripts, 1772-1834 (Box 9)
    - Coleridge, Samuel Taylor Correspondence, 1772-1834 (Box 10)
    - Com - G (Box 11)
    - Field, Barron [facsimile] "Memoirs of the Life and Poetry of William Wordsworth", 1786-1846 (Box 12)
    - Hamilton - Howard (Box 13)
    - Hudson - Jamieson (excluding Hutchinson) (Box 14)
    - Hutchinson, A - Hutchinson, J (Box 15)
    - Hutchinson, K - Hutchinson, R (Box 16)
    - Hutchinson, Sara (Box 17)
    - Hutchinson, Sara - end of Hutchinson (Box 18)
    - K - L (Box 19)
    - M - Monkhouse, John, letters through 1809, 1809 (Box 20)
    - Monkhouse, John, letters 1810 - N, 1810 (Box 21)
    - O - P (Box 22)
    - Q - Reed, Henry, letters through 1841, 1841 (Box 23)
    - Reed, Henry, letters 1842 - Rz, 1842 (Box 24)
    - S- Sn (Box 25)
    - Southey, Caroline Anne, Charles Cuthbert, Edith (Fricker), Robert (Box 26)
    - Sp - V (Box 27)
    - W - Wordsworth, Christopher, Sr., letters through 1810, 1810 (Box 28)
    - Wordsworth, Christopher, Sr., letters 1810 - Wordsworth, Christopher, Jr., 1810 (Box 29)
    - Wordsworth, Dora, (later) Quillinan (Box 30)
    - Wordsworth, Dorothy (Box 31)
    - Wordsworth, Elizabeth - Wordsworth, John (Box 32)
    - Wordsworth, Mary (Hutchinson) through 1829, 1829 (Box 33)
    - Wordsworth, Mary (Hutchinson), 1830 - 1859 (Box 34)
    - Wordsworth, Priscilla (Lloyd) - Z, unknown (Box 35)
- Bound manuscripts
  Manuscripts by or relating to Wordsworth, including poems, prose, letters, and journals.
  - Harriet L. Barnes, Journal of a tour to the Lakes in the autumn of 1840, Circa 1840; 2
  - William Wordsworth, The brothers: a pastoral poem, 1799-1800; 3 +
  - Baron George Gordon Byron, Lord Byron "Childe Harold" proofs and letter, Circa 1834-1837; 4 +
  - Baron George Gordon Byron, Lord Byron story and letter page with seal, 1822-1823; 5 +
  - Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Letter to Thomas Clarkson, Oct. 13, 1806; 6 +
  - Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Letter to Parry, Jun. 25, 1799; 7 tiny
  - The Cottle album, 1656-1828; 8 ++
  - Thomas De Quincey, Notes on Wordsworth's Convention of Cintra, 1809; 9
  - Harry Goodwin, Pen and ink drawings illustrating Wordsworth's poems, 1883-1887; 10 +
  - Everett M. Hankins, Literary criticism by William Wordsworth, 1949; 11-13 +
  - Fanny Johnstone, "Dorothy Wordsworth" play, Circa 1830-1899; 14 +
  - Lady Diana Le Fleming, Le Fleming family account books, 1809-1823; 15-17
  - Charles Lloyd, Isabel, a domestick tale, or, Godwin vs. Godwin, Circa 1800; 18-19
  - Rachel Myers Meakin, Album, 1845; 20
  - C. Partridge and M. Partridge, Smiles and tears, Circa 1840; 21 +
  - Cynthia Morgan St. John, Scrapbook on Wordsworth, 1892-1955; 22 ++
  - Emily Trevenen, Album, 1829; 23
  - J.R. Tutin, The Wordsworth year-book, Circa 1890; 24 +
  - Cynthia Morgan St. John, A scrap book of parodies, Circa 1900-1919; 25
  - A Wordsworth scrap-book, 1890s; 26 ++
  - Dora Wordsworth, Commonplace book, 1823-1868; 27
  - Foreign inns, 1800s; 28
  - William Wordsworth, Poem and note, Circa 1839; 29 ++
  - William and Mary Wordsworth, Notebook, Circa 1833; 30 tiny
  - Wordsworth portrait and letter, Circa 1828; 31
  - Wordsworth portraits and letter, Circa 1800-1848; 32 ++
  - William Wordsworth, Poems in two volumes, Circa 1807; 33 +++
  - Silhouette portrait album of the Hutchinson family, 1827; 352 tiny
  - Benjamin Robert Haydon, Album, Circa 1830-1839; 353 +
  - Lake District scrapbook, 1888-1919; 354 ++
  - Dove cottage films and xerographs in the Department of Rare Books, Cornell University Library, 1964; 355 +
- Wordsworthiana and Other Material
  - Wordsworth's sense of place home at Grasmere written and presented by Sally Bushell., 2008; 450
  - Reviews, Pamphlets, etc. (Box 2)
  - Sotheby's Auction Photocopies (Box 36)
  - Wordsworthiana Keepsakes (Box 37)
  - Wordsworthiana Portraits (Box 38)
  - Wordsworthiana Homes and Haunts (Box 39)
- Dove Cottage manuscripts, photocopies
  Photocopies of originals at Dove Cottage, Grasmere, England. Manuscripts by or relating to Wordsworth, including poems, prose, letters, and Dorothy Wordsworth's journals.
  These items are stored off site. To request them, search in the Library's online catalog under title "Dove Cottage manuscripts" and follow the appropriate "Request delivery to the RMC reading room" link from there.
  - William Wordsworth, Lines written as a school exercise at Hawkshead, D.C. Ms. Verse 1, photocopy, Circa 1785-1786; 35
  - William Wordsworth, Three poems written at Hawkshead, D.C. Ms. Verse 2, photocopy, 1786; 36
  - William Wordsworth, The vale of Esthwaite, D.C. Ms. Verse 3, photocopy, Circa 1787; 37
  - William Wordsworth, The starling, Beauty and moonlight: an ode, The dog, Duge sung by a minstrel, Pseudo-Spenserian stanzas, Extracts from The vale of Esthwaite, D.C. Ms. Verse 4, photocopy, 1786-1787, 1793-1794; 38
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of translation of Georgics IV and of The vale of Esthwaite, D.C. Ms. Verse 5, photocopy, 1786-1788; 39 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments written at Cambridge and Hawkshead, D.C. Ms. Verse 6, photocopy, 1787-1788; 40 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of An evening walk, Lines on the horse, Translation of Horace: Odes I 31, D.C. Ms. Verse 7, photocopy, 1788-1789; 41
  - William Wordsworth, 1793 edition of An evening walk (two copies with ms. corrections), D.C. Ms. Verse 8-9, photocopy, Circa 1793; 42
  - William Wordsworth, An evening walk, with additions written at Windy Brow, D.C. Ms. Verse 10, photocopy, 1794; 43
  - William Wordsworth, Incidents upon Salisbury Plain, Variants of Salisbury Plain, An evening walk (with lines not found in ed. of 1793), an unpublished poem to Mary in imitation of Horace's Septimi Gades, From the Greek, From the French, Inscription for Windy Brow, D.C. Ms. Verse 11, photocopy, Jun. 1794 and earlier; 44
  - William Wordsworth, Notebook from Racedown, D.C. Ms. Verse 12, photocopy, 1795-1796 and earlier; 45 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Essay originally prefaced to The borderers, D.C. Ms. Verse 13, photocopy, 1795; 46
  - William Wordsworth, Early draft of part of The borderers, D.C. Ms. Verse 14, photocopy, 1795-1796; 47
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude, The borderers (Ms. 2), D.C. Ms. Verse 15, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 48
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude, The borderers (Ms. 2), D.C. Ms. Verse 15, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 49
  - William Wordsworth, The borderers, D.C. Ms. Verse 16, photocopy, 1841-1842; 50
  - William Wordsworth, The borderers (Ms. 4, final ms. as returned for the printers), D.C. Ms. Verse 17, photocopy, 1841-1842; 51
  - William Wordsworth, Christabel, D.C. Ms. Verse 18, part 1, photocopy, Circa 1800; 52
  - William Wordsworth, Christabel, D.C. Ms. Verse 18, part 2, photocopy, Circa 1800; 53
  - William Wordsworth, Matthew poems, Fragments of The Prelude, Fragments of The excursion, A character, Nutting, Andrew Jones, Salisbury Plain, D.C. Ms. Verse 18A, photocopy, Circa 1793-1794; 54
  - William Wordsworth, The Alfoxden notebook, D.C. Ms. Verse 19, photocopy, Circa 1797-1798; 55
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. A), D.C. Ms. Verse 20, photocopy, 1805-1806; 56
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. A), D.C. Ms. Verse 20, photocopy, 1805-1806; 57
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. B), D.C. Ms. Verse 21, photocopy, 1805-1806; 58
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. B), D.C. Ms. Verse 21, photocopy, 1805-1806; 59
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. C), D.C. Ms. Verse 22, photocopy, 1817-1819; 60
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. C), D.C. Ms. Verse 22, photocopy, 1817-1819; 61
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. D), D.C. Ms. Verse 23, photocopy, 1824-1828, corrected 1832 and 1839; 62
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. D), D.C. Ms. Verse 23, photocopy, 1824-1828, corrected 1832 and 1839; 63
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude, D.C. Ms. Verse 24, books 1-4, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 64
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude, D.C. Ms. Verse 24, books 5-7, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 65
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude, D.C. Ms. Verse 24, books 8-10, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 66
  - Dorothy Wordsworth, Recollections of a tour in Scotland, 1803, William Wordsworth, The prelude, D.C. Ms. Verse 24, books 11-14, photocopy, 1805-1806; 67
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude, D.C. Ms. Verse 24, books 1-14, photocopy, 1798-1805; 68
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. M), D.C. Ms. Verse 25, photocopy, 1804-1805; 69
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. M), D.C. Ms. Verse 25, photocopy, 1804-1805; 70
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. V), D.C. Ms. Verse 26, photocopy, Circa 1798; 71
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. V), D.C. Ms. Verse 26, photocopy, Circa 1798; 72
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. W), D.C. Ms. Verse 27, photocopy, 1802-1804; 73
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. W), D.C. Ms. Verse 27, photocopy, 1802-1804; 74
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. X), D.C. Ms. Verse 28, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 75
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. X), D.C. Ms. Verse 28, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 76
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. Y), D.C. Ms. Verse 29, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 77
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. Y), D.C. Ms. Verse 29, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 78
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. Z), D.C. Ms. Verse 30, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 79
  - William Wordsworth, The prelude (Ms. Z), D.C. Ms. Verse 30, photocopy, Circa 1798-1805; 80
  - William Wordsworth, Incipient madness, D.C. Ms. Verse 31, photocopy, 1795-1798; 81
  - William Wordsworth, The ruined cottage, D.C. Ms. Verse 32, photocopy, Circa 1796-1798; 82
  - William Wordsworth, The ruined cottage (Excursion I, Ms. B), D.C. Ms. Verse 33B, photocopy, Circa 1800; 83
  - William Wordsworth, The ruined cottage (Excursion I, Ms. E), D.C. Ms. Verse 33E, photocopy, Circa 1800; 84
  - William Wordsworth, Peter Bell, D.C. Ms. Verse 34, photocopy, Circa 1800; 85
  - William Wordsworth, Peter Bell, D.C. Ms. Verse 35, photocopy, Circa 1800; 86 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Peter Bell, D.C. Ms. Verse 36, photocopy, Circa 1800; 87 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 37, photocopy, Circa 1800; 88 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Poems probably sent to Thomas Poole in 1800, D.C. Ms. Verse 37A, photocopy, Circa 1800; 89
  - William Wordsworth, The recluse, D.C. Ms. Verse 38, 41, photocopy, 1800; 90
  - William Wordsworth, The recluse (Ms. 1), D.C. Ms. Verse 39, photocopy, 1800; 91
  - William Wordsworth, The recluse (Ms. 2), D.C. Ms. Verse 40, photocopy, Circa 1800; 92
  - William Wordsworth, Poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 42, photocopy, Circa 1800; 93 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 43, photocopy, Circa 1800; 94 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, The cuckoo and the nightengale, The prioress' tale, Argument for suicide, Old man travelling, D.C. Ms. Verse 44, photocopy, 1795-1798, 1801; 95
  - William Wordsworth, The prioress' tale, D.C. Ms. Verse 45, photocopy, 1801; 96
  - William Wordsworth, The manciple's tale, D.C. Ms. Verse 46, photocopy, 1801; 97
  - William Wordsworth, Fragment of Troilus and Cressida, D.C. Ms. Verse 47, photocopy, 1801; 98
  - William Wordsworth, When, to the attractions of the busy world, D.C. Ms. Verse 48, photocopy, 1801-1805; 99
  - William Wordsworth, To the cuckoo, D.C. Ms. Verse 49, photocopy, Circa 1800-1805; 100
  - William Wordsworth, Address to my infant daughter, D.C. Ms. Verse 50, photocopy, 1804; 101
  - William Wordsworth, Fidelity, D.C. Ms. Verse 51, photocopy, 1805; 102
  - William Wordsworth, Verses in memory of Capt. John Wordsworth, transcribed by Sara Hutchinson, D.C. Ms. Verse 51A, photocopy, 1805; 103 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Benjamin the Waggoner, D.C. Ms. Verse 52, photocopy, 1806; 104
  - William Wordsworth, Benjamin the Waggoner, Peter Bell, Artegal and Elidure, transcribed by Sara Hutchinson, D.C. Ms. Verse 52A, photocopy, 1815-1817; 105 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, From Bolton's old monastic tower, D.C. Ms. Verse 53, photocopy, Circa 1805; 106
  - William Wordsworth, Poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 54, photocopy, Circa 1808; 107 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Epistle to Sir G. Beaumont, Maternal grief, D.C. Ms. Verse 55, photocopy, 1837-1842; 108
  - William Wordsworth, Black Combe, D.C. Ms. Verse 56, photocopy, 1811 or 1813; 109
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of The excursion, Books I and III, D.C. Ms. Verse 57, photocopy, 1806; 110
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of The excursion, mostly Book IV, D.C. Ms. Verse 58, photocopy, Circa 1806; 111 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of The excursion, Books I-III, D.C. Ms. Verse 59, photocopy, Circa 1806; 112 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of The excursion, Books IV, VI, and IX, D.C. Ms. Verse 60, photocopy, Circa 1806; 113
  - William Wordsworth, The excursion, Book V, D.C. Ms. Verse 61, part 1, photocopy, Circa 1806; 114
  - William Wordsworth, The excursion, Book V, fragments of Books V-IX, D.C. Ms. Verse 61, part 2, photocopy, Circa 1806; 115
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of The excursion and The Prelude, D.C. Ms. Verse 61, part 3, photocopy, Circa 1806; 116
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of The excursion, Books V and VII-IX, D.C. Ms. Verse 62, photocopy, Circa 1806; 117
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of The excursion, D.C. Ms. Verse 62A, photocopy, Circa 1806; 118 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Vaudracour and Julia, D.C. Ms. Verse 63, photocopy, Circa 1815-1820; 119
  - William Wordsworth, A little onward..., D.C. Ms. Verse 64, photocopy, 1816; 120
  - William Wordsworth, A help for the memory of the Grand Independent, D.C. Ms. Verse 65, photocopy, 1818; 121
  - William Wordsworth, Sonnets and poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 66, photocopy, 1818; 122 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, The River Duddon and other sonnets and poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 67A, photocopy, 1816; 123
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of sonnets and poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 67B, photocopy, Circa 1819; 124 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of Dogmatic teachers and Duddon sonnet no. 29, D.C. Ms. Verse 68, photocopy, Circa 1820; 125
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments of book written in preparation for 1820 volume, D.C. Ms. Verse 69, photocopy, Circa 1817; 126
  - William Wordsworth, Memorials of a tour on the continent, 1820, D.C. Ms. Verse 70, photocopy, 1822; 127
  - William Wordsworth, Memorials of a tour on the continent, 1820, D.C. Ms. Verse 70, photocopy, 1822; 128
  - William Wordsworth, To the Lady le Fleming, D.C. Ms. Verse 71, photocopy, 1823; 129
  - William Wordsworth, Cenotaph in remembrance of Frances Fermor, D.C. Ms. Verse 72, photocopy, 1824; 130
  - William Wordsworth, The doubt to which a wavering hope had clung, D.C. Ms. Verse 73, photocopy, 1826; 131
  - William Wordsworth, The triad, The wishing gate, The gleamer, in hand of Sara Hutchinson, D.C. Ms. Verse 74, photocopy, 1828; 132 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, To our gold and silver fish, D.C. Ms. Verse 75, photocopy, 1829; 133
  - William Wordsworth, Humantiy and Liberty as one poem with the title To a friend, In these fair vales..., Haydon! Let worthier judges..., D.C. Ms. Verse 76, photocopy, Circa 1829; 134
  - William Wordsworth, Miscellaneous poems, D.C. Ms. Verse 77, photocopy, Circa 1830; 135
  - William Wordsworth, The somnabulist, The poet and the caged turtledove, The Russian fugitive, D.C. Ms. Verse 78, photocopy, Circa 1830-1835; 136
  - William Wordsworth, Lines suggested by a portrait from the pencil of F. Stone, D.C. Ms. Verse 79, photocopy, 1834; 137
  - William Wordsworth, Poems mostly incorporated in Yarrow revisited, D.C. Ms. Verse 80, photocopy, Circa 1826-1835; 138
  - William Wordsworth, Poems collected for Yarrow revisited, D.C. Ms. Verse 81, photocopy, 1835; 139
  - William Wordsworth, Poems included in Yarrow revisited, chiefly transcribed by Dora Wordsworth, D.C. Ms. Verse 81A, photocopy, Circa 1833; 140 tiny
  - William Wordsworth, Poems mostly incorporated in Yarrow revisited, D.C. Ms. Verse 81B, photocopy, Before 1835; 141
  - William Wordsworth, Poems mostly incorporated in Yarrow revisited, D.C. Ms. Verse 81B, photocopy, Before 1835; 142
  - William Wordsworth, Yarrow revisited no. XXVI, D.C. Ms. Verse 82, photocopy, 1834; 143
  - William Wordsworth, Yarrow revisited no. XXVI, D.C. Ms. Verse 82, photocopy, 1834; 144
  - William Wordsworth, Fragments connected with Yarrow revisited, D.C. Ms. Verse 83, photocopy, 1835; 145
  - William Wordsworth, Fair copies of poems included in Yarrow revisited, D.C. Ms. Verse 84, photocopy, 1835; 146
  - William Wordsworth, Yarrow revisited manuscript returned from the printer, incomplete, D.C. Ms. Verse 85, photocopy, 1835; 147
  - William Wordsworth, Yarrow revisited corrected proofs, 1st revision, incomplete, D.C. Ms. Verse 86, photocopy, 1835; 148
  - William Wordsworth, Yarrow revisited corrected proofs, 2nd revision, incomplete, D.C. Ms. Verse 87, photocopy, 1835; 149
  - William Wordsworth, Airey Force Valley, D.C. Ms. Verse 88, photocopy, Sept. 1836; 150
  - William Wordsworth, Early drafts of the six sonnets added to the 1838 edition of Passport..., D.C. Ms. Verse 89, photocopy, 1837; 151
  - William Wordsworth, The cuckoo at Laverna, D.C. Ms. Verse 90, photocopy, 1837; 152
  - William Wordsworth, Sonnet suggested in Italy, D.C. Ms. Verse 91, photocopy, 1837-1846; 153